so
um if I think about past memories when I
was 5 10 20 30 to my present experience
and there's a sense of continuity or
itself to who knows
to who knows
um experiences
happened which also informs
thoughts about the future
um so I was wondering
could that sense of continuity be one
way to describe what Baba is
um yes certainly yeah it's it's a form
of well it's the way you exist yeah
so um
but see that continuity
from your past
that you can recollect now
where is that continuity perceived
no exactly yeah the colors the past
with the same owner
but it's actually here and now
and back when that you know 10 years ago
when Dad was here and now that's where
that sense of continuity sense of I am
that possessed throughout these
different experiences that's what it was
it was here and now it's always here and
now that's where that Central continuit
is
that sense of I am sense of self
so but it wasn't advocating to deny
this sense of continuity so he was more
seeing no sense of continuity is real as
such they made the mistake though is the
mistake of ownership yeah and and that's
the mistake that's uh again uh
perpetuated on the basis of a mind
that's not free from Green division Here
and Now
so that's why a person who would have
uprooted the ownership Freedom mind from
conceiving from the notion of I am fully
developed anata as the Buddha says in
the sutras that person would not think
oh but I was in the past now I'm not
because I'm an arahunt but I was in the
past and I or I would be in the future
no past and future were equally affected
by that same present that has been
purified so he's fully seeing the sense of
so he's fully seeing the sense of
continuity as contained within that
which is discontinuous yeah yeah he seen
his fully fully uh uh unknownable fully
dependent on the uh
existence and operation of the of the
five Aggregates on their presence
yeah there is no there is no um that
because that's that's the trick with
that sense of continuity and the sense
of I am sense of self it feels like
um it's outside of the experience as a
whole as a as a Perpetual entity owner
to whom these things occur feelings
perceptions past future but it exists
independent of them
so it's it's changing that order through
right contemplation that can only arise
on the basis of of virtue and sense
restraint um but that's when when then you start
um but that's when when then you start
to reverse you start seeing so you're
not denying you're not denying the sense
of I am you're not denying the sense of
that continuous sense of self that you
remember since you were a child but
you're just including it within the
Arisen present there isn't feeling
present there isn't perception intention
State of Mind
um so basically you're putting it second
you're you're enclosing it where it
should be enclosed so that that the
Traders sense of
um
oh this is something outside independent
of these feelings then come and go
perceptions come and go that will fade
away see people people have the view and the
see people people have the view and the
assumption that their sense of self is
independent of the experience as a whole
because that's they're cultivating
through their attitude and through
Direction so if you stop cultivating you stop
so if you stop cultivating you stop
providing fuel for it it will fade away
because it's not actually
on the outside it's not actually
independent
um whenever a
um brought up a Suitor relating to this
I was only gone yes I'm
yes we've interrogate my interpretation
that yeah
so it's a magic manika 74.
there are three kinds of feeling
Pleasant feeling painful feeling and
neutral feeling on the occasion when one
feels Pleasant feeling one does not feel
painful or neutral feeling
on that occasion one feels only Pleasant
feeling and the occasion when one feels painful
and the occasion when one feels painful
feeling one does not feel Pleasant or
neutral feeling on that occasion one
feels only painful feeling on the
occasion when one feels neutral feeling
one does not feel Pleasant or painful
feeling on that occasion one feels only
Mutual feeling
um so yeah
so my interpretation is that basically
it's highlighting
what comes first yeah exactly the
discontinuity of feeling as a container
for your experience as a whole well see
but by by regarding
currently enduring feeling is that which
is first
means that's the entirety of your
container of a present experience so whether you
of a present experience so whether you
are now having
remembering something from your past
planning for the future
that is done within the cartoon enduring
feeling it's just the people's attitude of their
it's just the people's attitude of their
own feelings and perceptions as I said
they put them second
so they don't recognize that
um not just that there is a pleasant uh
feel like if there is a pleasant feeling
currently present that's the only
feeling you feel as The Suitor says but
that's really your entire existence is
within that kind of feeling that endures
and when the new feeling comes up so to
speak when this feeling ceases and next thing
when this feeling ceases and next thing
you know now you're feeling unpleasant
feeling for whatever reason when you
become self-aware of it you find it as
already there being felt and you are
within it
so there is no point in between one
feeling that then passes into next
feeling because that point will require
you to step outside of your experience
as a whole and observe that change from
one to two to three but you are within
it so all you have is the enclosure of
this kind of this color of this feeling
and then within that you're thinking
planning acting forgetting greed
aversion delusion or sensory strain
virtue or
and then oh now I find myself within
another feeling oh how did that happen
well that becomes irrelevant question
it matters to somebody how did feeling
change from one to the other can I
observe the moment in between a person
who will be asking those questions is
the person that refuses to give up the
view or is unable to give up the view
because he's not aware of it of the
external sense of self that observes
this and they want to monitor this
change which is what like sensuality a
world exactly all of these unwholesome
states rely on that perversion of that
same order so the point here is then to
recognize that okay so I might really
feel that it's important to find an
answer how this feeling abruptly now I
feel this abruptly now I feel neutral
feeling of our play now it's pleasure
abruptly and so on how does that change
from one to the other the pressure for
that question you need to basically
subdue and and not waste your time
trying to answer because you're going to
fall into speculative view because again
if you're very careful and and
transparent you realize it's an you'll
be unable you cannot possibly think
outside of yourself from from which
point you will have a neutral reference
that tells you how one feeling for you
while it's being felt becomes another
and perceives so you realize any notion
of answering this requires the notion of
that external World independent of my
five Aggregates and that's fundamental
wrong View
so instead of then trying to answer it
or trying to observe it through a
meditation technique like to to narrow
down the moments doesn't matter how
closely You observe one moment to the
next moment the change between one to
the next is always abrupt
it's not something you can see because
if you were to see the change between
moment a to moment B well there would be
another moment in other words anything
that you can observe is within that
experience that already endures it's
within that feeling it's within that
five Aggregates basically that cannot be
stepped outside of
so that's the the Practical point of
that suit is exactly to recognize that
doesn't matter how specific moment how
specific the moment I'm observing might
be doesn't matter how uh you know
pleasing and elaborate and satisfactory
my explanation of the external
process of change or flux can be
fundamentally all of that is secondary
to the present enduring feeling
whichever that feeling is
so four is long so it's not about
um changing that feeling it's not about
seeing how it changes from externally
it's about not putting it second while
it lasts
so that he knows that in the current
container of the experience as a whole
whereby a neutral feeling is currently
present that's the only feeling felt
there everything else is second to it
everything else is second to it
and maintain that order and then what
then what's next thing what what what
well next thing is when you exactly ask
that question what do I do next you see
oh is that another feeling or is still
the same feeling that's present if it's
still the same feeling you include that
question a second to that presently
endearing feeling and thus you don't
lose the right order but if you then
find out yourself oh this is I feel
unpleasant now
instead of how did it come to be in
psychologist about it you start
recognizing okay that's the only feeling
felt yeah but that past feeling that I
remember it's now the memory the
perception within this presently
enduring unpleasant feeling
so there is no one container as a whole
morphing into next one all you have is
one one
in other words five Aggregates five
Aggregates five Aggregates or in another
words as a suitable describe five
Aggregates are fading in five hours
fading away fading in fading away that's
all you have coming and going rising and
falling whichever way you describe it on
the level of the experience as a whole
and that's why like Buddha vipassi he
contemplated that arising in ceasing
rising and falling of the five
aggregates for a complete Liberation for the
for a complete Liberation for the
complete harahanship and becoming some
Assam Buddha
because if you contemplate every single
reason experience as a whole as a
contender itself that endures for as
long as it wants to endure so to speak
and any notion of sense of self I am
conceit present future uh loves fears
what is anything any passion greed
aversion distraction any hindrance you
might have you put that second
within this present enduring container
you do not pervert the order basically
there will be the only the only possible
result of that is dispassion
nothing else
and in the nutshell that's exactly the
practice of satipatana
so this mentions the three feelings as
the point but you realize you could
practice exactly the same principle on
the level of the body posture or simply
on the level of the body being there as
a necessary container for any past
present future memories hindrances and
so on
feeling Perceptions in the sense of uh
State of Mind you perceive your state of
mind what is my mood what is my general
mood is it elated depressed so instead
of thinking like you are this entity
that goes through these different moods
you recognize is no these different
moods keep containing this entity that I
keep confusing it to be the same person
the same
the same phenomenon that exists now
independent of these moods but that's
impossible or uh dumbass just in general
the four Sati patana is just the dumbest
the actual phenomena in that most
precise phenomenological sense
phenomenological sense
every presence of every thought
on that phonological basis you realize
that well that's a container in and of
itself for this whole experience
it's what comes first it's what endures
not the continuity the sense of
continuous Santa continuity second and
once you put it second well it ceases to
be that continuous thing that exists
outside of your sense of of your
experience as a whole
you can't
choose not to have the sense of
continuity this is the only way to work
exactly is that change the order yeah to
say like I'm refusing to have the sense
of continuity and that sense of
continuity basically is what it's kind
of would kind of remain to some extent
so when complete this passion is
developed in a case of another hunt that
sense of continuity is what what's
called a pugala what's called individual
what's called basically the the history
of these five Aggregates the the habits
the the the ways it was operating that
are now freed from great diversion
delusion freed from these influxes of
asavas and pollutions but to some extent
they remain standing there for as long
as the father grades don't break apart
so that that sense of continuity will
not be confused for the sense of self
independent of the feeling of the
perception of the mood of the dhammas of
the body it will simply be yeah it's
these same five Aggregates they've been
enduring for this long and that's the
non-persisting oil changing in the
angutura 3 47. yeah it's yeah but
obviously it's impossible as a non-air
had to
to like yeah imagine that or conceive
that but it's something you can't well
if you're conceiving it that's already a
mistake yeah it's going to be conceiving
yeah so the only way is to to uh as I
said you won't provide or you can try
but and you can provide an answer but it
will never be accurate because providing
an answer requires that uh external
point of view of what's Happening Here
and Now moment to moment to moment yeah
um and doesn't matter how hard you
concentrate within moment to moment
you're still doing it internally you're
still doing it as as
someone who is fully enclosed by each
moment so it doesn't matter how many
moments you observed you're equally
enclosed within each and every one of
them that's it every single time and the more
that's it every single time and the more
you narrow in between the moments well
that's another moment you're enclosed
with so there is no way out through it
so there is no way out through it
through that concentrating techniques or
or obviously through like a speculative
mystical experiences that take you
outside of yourself it's impossible
everything you've experienced is on the
basis of your experience
doesn't matter if it's unfamiliar if
it's unknown
still experience real as such
so the recognition is then is to to
discern rightly with the Right View this
correctly enduring reference points body
feeling moods State of Mind
so that's when you recognize that you
don't get rid of the feeling you don't
get real estate to mind you just see it
for what it is to the extent that it is
and that's exactly what describes like
he knows elated mind as elated mind
that's it to the extent it the mind is
as such he knows it as such he knows
depressed mind as depressed mind
he knows it so he does not observe it or
tries to psychologize it or find a way
out of it he simply knows it and that
means he puts it in the right place
he knows it as first and everything else
every pressure any other hindrance they
might want to make you doubt it change
it do this do that
he puts a second within the enduring
state of mind or within the enduring
state of feeling
and that's the contemplation
so you could say the the essential
difference is basically instead of
seeing [Music] [Music]
things
or trying to see feeling as a thing that
you can
act towards against
it's basically like you said to see it
as being there beforehand before before
you even exactly can exactly and that's
that's what you can even act towards it
or again that's a point also might not
be clear on the base of what I said but
that's yeah so when you uh find yourself
already feeling such and such feeling
that's that's like the key is to
recognize there was no like first moment
from which you saw that feeling start
because that implies you were there
before the feeling outside of the
feeling no you already find whether it's
the body posture whether it's the
feeling whether it's the State of Mind
mood whether it's the dumbass you find
them as already there given beforehand
they're already there you've found it
you recollected them you brought them up
but they were there and that's that
recognition ah so they did not originate
from you
uh you know the Creator you find them
and then you act out of them and by
doing so you appropriate them you put
yourself first and by putting yourself
first you become the owner of these
things even pains and bad moves that you
don't want that's what people like
can't help
but feel affected by the bad mood a bad
feeling can't help but take it as as
yours they don't mind they can't just
say oh I won't take it as mine why well
because on other occasions they keep
taking it as mine through perverting
that order that's all it takes
so you would you would not be observing
that feeling how it lasts you would
simply find it there know it as an
enduring container and your sense of
self that's used to be regarded as the
owner as the one who acts who sorts the
feelings out who who manages them this
all of that your first restraint in
order to place it second within the
enduring container of the filling for
how long you do it well for as long as
they're feeling for until that feeling
changes and that feeling changes then you find
and that feeling changes then you find
yourself feeling another feeling as The
Suitor says all you can feel is one
feeling at the time
so what you do then you do the same
thing so obviously in if it's the pleasant
so obviously in if it's the pleasant
feeling that you're enduring the Leaning
that you would have to be restraining
and containing would be to prolong that
pressure pleasure to get more of it if
it's unpleasant feeling that you're
enduring the Leaning that you would have
to be restraining
the Leaning that you would have to be
restraining is aversion towards it to
get rid of it
and if it's unneutral if it's a neutral
feeling that you're currently enclosed
Within uh well what you have to restrain is
uh well what you have to restrain is
basically indolence distraction boredom
uh delusion not not knowing that feeling
for what it is that neutrality on
account of what's being felt
could you describe those as I like
craving aversion distraction as they're
trying to employ
continuity in a way trying to yes
continuity will pressure you basically
one again not continuity the sense of
ownership the sense of self the sense of
craving the habit of putting yourself
first the weight of that will pressure you
the weight of that will pressure you
will want to maintain itself
the momentum of it so so that's that's
kind of the
um what you need to kind of work against
yes um and uh and when that weight
um and uh and when that weight
disappears then it becomes inconceivable
to actually change the order because you
realize the order was never changed
impermanence was always impermanence
anata was always an Atta an ownership
was always things that are unknownable
they would run on them it was just you
being completely deluded in regard to it
so it basically employ continuity means
cover up the factual discontinuity that
is unavoidable yeah yeah because as I
said initially that that uh the weight
on that um on the sense of self being
put first
that will pressure you basically to
maintain it there because it's going to
feel unpleasantly if you start shifting
that weight away from it because you
know if sense of self that's based on
the sense of control and ownership if
you start contemplating non-controlling
non-ownership well that sense of self
are gonna resist it's gonna resist a bit
it's gonna it's not gonna take it
lightly
in terms of establishing the right order
you get to maybe you get the idea of
what that is that you are second to The
Container within experience
very confined
and you want to
try to keep that
Vision you know
so
and the only way to see that again
sense restraints and so on
helps the clarifying your situation but
essentially in itself
being aware being present moment doesn't
give you that right order that vision
so because what what you are present
moment to moment is your perverted order
and you you don't know the order you
don't know what comes first so
practicing moment-to-moment awareness or
whatever they describe you these days
all you're practicing is moment to
moment perversion of the earth it
remains unchanging just be mindful of
yourself of whatever whatever is there
and you don't even know where the
problem is yeah
and that's why body speech your mind see
you can gather get the sense of the
right order
like through pondering through reflecting and
through pondering through reflecting and
so on
but if you're still reverting it to
bodily actions well it's not going to
take root if you're perverting it
through verbal actions it's not gonna
it's not gonna grow and if you're
perverting instrumental actions and
perverting it to body speech or mind
it's exactly acting out of greediversion
delusion it takes you away from that from having
it takes you away from that from having
perspective or
well because they those those phenomena
phenomenal greed aversion desire
sensuality uh that is a phenomenon of
perverted order so choosing to act upon
it is it equals to choosing to prefer
the order even if you don't necessarily
think in those terms that's where it's
unwholesome just in and of itself
I will control these feelings I will
produce these again you might not even
think those thoughts at all but that's
the implication basically put yourself
first so whenever there is a desire involved
so whenever there is a desire involved
ill will distraction you put yourself
first so you can contemplate on top of
it the right order all you want if your
actions are still putting yourself first
in that fundamental existential sense
well as I said the right order cannot
possibly begin to grow
and everything else they would they
would come from
so a person wants to put themselves
second in this right sense and you have
a strong
feelings of pain hmm
and instead of trying to
sort that pain out yeah you just
put it put yourself
first you need to not act out of the
pressure to sew the feeling out that is
like you have to you have to let it
endure for what it is
but it's not to say oh just endure it
blindly like a fool and it will just
wisdom will come out of it no of course
not so first you don't act out of it it has
so first you don't act out of it it has
to endure for what it is so that you
then see your diversion towards it
and put a second
and when you put a second it's gone as
in pituitous unnecessary exactly as it
completely within the origin feeling
that's present enduring there is no
outside of it
and when you put your reversion second
the pressure to act out of that aversion
dissipates almost instantaneously when
the right order is established even for
a finger snap as the suitcase would say
for that finger snap The Liberation is
felt so the point there is to then recognize
so the point there is to then recognize
that okay out of Faith initially you
don't act out of trying to sort out the
unpleasant feeling and so on you
recognize your aversion towards it so
you you basically include the version
within the painted endures and not act
out of it uh
and as I said the pressure to act out
will diminish if you do it rightly and
then secondly uh then you also get to
recognize that that feeling that you
found as already being there are risen
on its own that's why it's gonna go away
on its own as well without you needing
to that out at all out of anything it
doesn't yeah so the recognition of this
manifested feeling becomes the oh it's
manifestation is its unmanifestation it
has to unmanif unmanifest because it's
manifested and I don't need to do anything so
and I don't need to do anything so
whatever has manifested that's why it
has to unmanifest not because it's like
this or like that but I did this what I
said this no no simply because it is it
will not be
and that in and of itself liberates you
from anything everything's the wholesome
Sara if it's fully developed
came on its own
endures on its own
no room for you there
and that's the recognition of satapan as
we mentioned before
whatever has the nature to manifest
that's why it will manifest
so you don't need to wait for it quite
the opposite you can't wait for thing to
end to see its own manifestation or to
see its impermanence
now you see it while the thing is there
and that's the recognition that
manifestation anything that's manifested
in your experience
as a whole on the level of the five
Aggregates because it's manifested
that's why it has to unmanifest
including the sense of continuity
including any any doesn't matter far
near subtle course broad General
particular any phenomenon to the extent
that it's manifested to the extent that
it's present
that that's why it will unmanifest
that's it
and put that first
put that container first
and protected there don't violate it
don't pervert it through your action by
Body speech and mind
so in terms of okay so again
putting yourself second
container first
and trying to keep that right order
trying to develop it so that it takes
root or that it everything flips
flips in the right way
keep precepts essential strains
and then there's the other exercise of
wakefulness continuous wake from this
practice of awakens and as as I said you
can't be wakeful and present and expect
that to to sort things out for you you
have to keep awake
and present with this right order yeah
yeah that's where the practice starts
with the with knowing the right order
knowing the Right View
so if you don't know what the right
order is everything else you do is kind
of circumstantial that that's not to say
that you shouldn't keep the precepts if
you're not a soda Banner but it's it's
to say that you should recognize that
you ought to recognize that the practice
begins with knowledge of the right order
first is first second and second you
know turning the upside down
but anyone correcting it wakefulness
yeah exactly away anybody can even sleep
forward but if people do that on the
basis of knowing the right order well
then they are actually progressing if
people keep anybody can keep the
precepts like a practice sense restraint
if people do that on the basis of the of
the knowledge of the right order well
that's pretty much the development of
the noble apop
is it you know you maintain wakefulness
to through the first watch of the night
hmm uh through the last watch of the night
uh through the last watch of the night
so through the day so the first watch of
the night and in the middle of the night
you go to sleep you get up and do the
same thing uh purify the Mind obstacles
yeah to work well what's an obstacle
exactly yeah so what you got to know you
have to have just randomly randomly
purifying your mind from things you
think you should they shouldn't be there
what are you building purifying the Mind
from things that are trying to pervert
the wrong the right order
are you removing the wrong order you
catch yourself putting yourself first
well there you go that's the in that's
an impurity
so you remove that impurity by fixing
the right order but by seeing what needs
to be seen as first and seeing what
needs to be seen a second
yeah also all those hindrances are
things which
you're trying to keep yeah
because you can yeah I just I was
reading that you know away from us you
know First Watch of the night don't go
to sleep for as long as you can go to
sleep in the middle wake up very early
and so on
and if someone takes it and do it in and
of itself in and of itself it can almost
drive you mad because yeah what do you
what are you doing yeah what are you
doing it for yeah
yeah no that's really like the the
emphasis the goal should be discernment of the
the goal should be discernment of the
right order
on the base of virtual sense restraint
that's the right view that's the sort of
party then you'll know what the practice
is
you will then also know how to protect
that right order and other things will
fall into place
but if you're just trying to do same
trying to do something
that's what keeps saying it applies only
to sort the panels are higher
you keep trying to do those things
thinking they in and of itself will
result in this recognition of you won't
you need to learn
what recognitions you have to understand
what the niche is on that right level
and and then it has to be endured there
until it's kind of seen correct you can
even listen to this talk read the sutas
get the sense or the right order and so
on but when say unpleasant feeling is
present what do you do
you're craving to to inversion to get
rid of it
are you able to contain it it is are you
able to put it second are you able to
then uphold the values of the right
order and not take out of it
for months if it takes that long for
that feeling to dissipate
or by the end of the day you have to act
out you have to say something you have
to address this because it becomes too
confining and you can't bear it anymore
so there you go that's why there is no
right view being developed because you
keep puncturing the container pretty
much you keep letting the pressure out
but if if you can't hold the pressure
well you need to then build up the
container to hold the pressure first but
that's what that's the thing that that
practice of awakens is doing is maintain
yeah they will intensify yeah maintain
it if it's done on the basis of the
gradual training when it comes to do
that you will be able to intensify it
like that but if you just do it as I
said as a some sort of practice
expecting that it will result in this
release you want well not of the release
that matters at least
never distract yourself
never giving to Indians never no turn
off that so even just a fail that you're
staying awake so if you've got the right
order you've got the idea of it yeah the
fact that you have you stay you you made
the determination to stay awake as long
as you can in the face of tiredness and
so on
kind of reminds you of your
determination yeah it is it is as I said
it is kind of pushing a bit further
testing it pressuring the the upholding
of the right order so to drain away any
impurities they might still be hiding
there further
deep inside
yeah because indolence is that all that
wanting to look away from that pressure
yeah want to distract yourself yeah it's
very strong yeah just forget forget
about it for a bit have a break from it
exactly yeah
obviously as I said somebody in the
beginning who doesn't have even the
right viewer who hasn't like cultivated
it
sufficiently enough those things are too
subtle to worry about them at that point
first address the course impurities you
don't start the suit as they describe
purifying the gold you don't purify the
gold by picking the microscopic bits out
but it's still like
lumps of mud you know flowing around
no you get the obvious stuff first out
then the less obvious and so on then
when there's nothing else you get to see
oh look now this is impurity in that
unless you won't even see it you just
covered with all the other dirt